Finding Aid for St. Paul’s Episcopal Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.) records, 1870-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Paul’s Episcopal Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.) records 1870-2005
St. Paul’s Episcopal Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.).
6 oversize volumes
8 linear feet
2008009 Ba 2
Episcopal church established in 1869 and defunct as of 2005. The record group includes registers of baptisms, marriages, burials, etc.; vestry minute books; historical and background information; and topical files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received as part of a larger accession from the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Western Michigan (donor no. 5247 ) received in January 2008.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
St. Paul's Memorial Church was founded in 1869 by St. Mark's Church, Grand Rapids to serve the west side of the city. The first church sanctuary on Turner Ave. was built in 1869 and consecrated in February 1870. The church was organized into a parish in May 1871 and admitted into the union of the Diocese of Western Michigan later that same year.
In the 1890s and early 1900s, the church under the leadership of Fr. Charles Donohue reached out to the new and growing community of Armenian immigrants to Grand Rapids. Donohue was also responsible for establishing St. Matthews Mission to the north end of Grand Rapids.
In the late 1950s, with the notification that its property would be taken over to make way for an expressway, St. Paul's began planning for a new facility. Located on Leonard Street, the new St. Paul's began holding services in 1962.
In the 1970s the Episcopal Church underwent reforms which would eventually split St. Paul's and lead to its closing. The issues included such matters as the ordination of women and homosexuals as priests, the updating of the Book of Common Prayer, and the church's pro-choice position on abortion. A majority of the church broke from the Episcopal Church and its liberal policies renaming themselves as St. Paul's Anglican Church. The Episcopal Diocese was forced to sue to regain possession of the church property. The church reopened in 1983 with the remnant who had supported the Diocese. The dissenters never returned. With a dwindling membership, St. Paul's closed, and the building de-consecrated in the summer of 2006.
The record group documents the entire history of the church from its founding in 1870 to its de-consecration in 2006. The earliest records are registers of baptisms, confirmation, burials, marriages, and similar church activities. Other records document the activities of the vestry and of the yearly parish meetings. Of special note are the records relating to the church split and its ramifications found mainly in the Topical files series of the record group.
Subjects:
Episcopal Church--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Church history.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; St. Paul's Episcopal Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Registers of baptisms, confirmation, burials, marriages, etc.
  - August 1870-July 1883 (Volume 1)
  - July 1883-December 1899 (Volume 2)
  - January 1900-December 1906 (Volume 3)
  - 1907-1942; include baptisms, 1907-June 1940, confirmations, 1907-1940, burials, 1907-June 1942 (Volume 4)
  - Marriages June 1906-May 1942 (Volume 5)
  - 1941-1949, 1956-1957; include baptisms, 1941-1949, confirmations, 1941-1947, burials, 1941-1948, January-May 1956, marriages, February 1943-August 1949, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1947-1959 include baptisms, February 1948-September 1959, confirmations, May 1947-March 1959, marriages, April 1948-December 1953, June 1958-April 1959, and burials, February 1948-November 1955 (Volume 6)
  - Communicants 1960-1994 (Box 1)
- Register of Church Services
  - 1923-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1974 (Box 1)
  - 1974-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1979-1989 (Box 1)
- Vestry
  - Minute books
    - 1934-1941 (Box 2)
    - 1941 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 2)
    - 1967-1975 (Box 2)
  - Vestry secretary record books
    - 1952-1997, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Monthly file
    - May 1997-December 2003 (Box 4)
    - January 2004-September 2005 (Box 5)
- Parish records
  - Annual parish meetings circa 1943-1978 (Box 5)
  - Parochial reports (Box 5)
- History with background and events information
  - Histories and anniversaries (Box 6)
  - Background information (Box 6)
  - Clippings (Box 6)
  - Albums containing photographs and clippings, 1 volumes; 3 folders (Box 6)
- Topical files
  - Alphabetical [A-V] and miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Church schism and related litigation (Box 8)
  - Church facilities: documents relating to various church buildings (Box 8)